A Guide to the Papers of the National Association of Pediatric Nurse Practitioners, 1972-1992
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
The Papers of theNational Association of Pediatric Nurse Practitioners 1972-1992
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-20
18 linear feet, 39 boxes (13 cm x 39.5 cm x 26.5 cm)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Center for Nursing Historical Inquiry Collection (CNHI). The Center for Nursing Historical Inquiry, established at the University of Virginia in 1991 to support historical scholarship in nursing, is dedicated to the preservation and study of nursing history in the United States. The goals of the Center include the collection of materials, the promotion of scholarship, and the dissemination of historical research findings. Since the NAPNAP collection is large, it was separated out from the rest of the CNHI collection (MS-8).
Biographical/Historical Information
The National Association of Pediatric Nurse Practitioners was founded in 1973 as a non-profit organization devoted to improving child health care and representing the interests of pediatric nurse practitioners/associates. In May of that year PNPs from around the country met in Columbus, Ohio to discuss affiliation with an existing nursing or medical professional group. They concluded that PNPs would best be served by their own specialty nursing organization, and scheduled a national meeting in October. At that meeting, with the unanimous vote of 400 PNPs, NAPNAP was born.
During the first few years NAPNAP focused on defining standards for PNP education and practice, on developing a certification process for PNPs, and on refining its organizational structure and goals. Early on, the organization also began to monitor health legislation and to actively marshal support among its constituents for specific legislative platforms. As NAPNAP matured, its activities expanded to include advising state boards of nursing, producing materials to educate consumers on childcare, and providing opportunities and funding for continuing education of PNPs. In 2002 NAPNAP serves over 6,500 members -- over 60% of PNPs nationally -- in 50 local chapters throughout the United States.
Scope and Content
The NAPNAP Collection consists primarily of administrative documents generated by the organization's executive director and staff and by its officers, committees, and task forces. These include correspondence, reports, meeting minutes, bylaws, applications for grants and awards, and conference materials. A large part of the collection is comprised of reports on health-related legislative issues generated by Capitol Associates, Inc., a Washington, D.C. lobbying firm. Smaller parts of the collection consist of: publications, including newsletters, conference programs, brochures, and position statements; photographs, mostly of conference activities; audiotapes of conference presentations; and videotapes of interviews with former officers and of educational and public service statements. The 1970s and 1980s are represented by scattered correspondence, reports, and publications. The full range of administrative documents begins in 1989.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into six series, reflecting the administrative structure and activities of the organization: Series 1: Administrative Office Documents; Series 2: Publications and manuals; Series 3: Chapters documents; Series 4: Photographs Series, 5: Audiotapes of conference programs; Series 6: Videotapes of interviews with former NAPNAP officers, public service and educational videos. (Note that videotapes have been separated from the main collection and are housed at the Center for Nursing Historical Inquiry.)
Contents List
- SERIES 1: Administrative Office Documents
  - Subseries: Historical Documents (Folder 1)
    - Subseries: History of NAPNAP 1983 - 1994 (Box-folder 001-001)
      Re: NAPNAP's first ten years, Phillis Cunningham's reminiscences of her NAPNAP experiences, and formation of NAPNAP archives
  - Subseries: Annual Reports and Bylaws
    - NAPNAP Operations Manual August 1977 (Box-folder 001-002)
      Re: rough draft of operations manual
    - Bylaws 1970s (Box-folder 001-003)
      Re: Bylaws
    - Bylaws 1980, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box-folder 001-004)
    - Bylaws 1991 (Box-folder 001-005)
    - Annual Reports 1975 - 1980 (Box-folder 001-006)
      Re: Annual reports
    - Annual Reports 1980 - 1983 (Box-folder 001-007)
    - Annual Reports 1984 - 1990 (Box-folder 001-008)
    - Annual Reports 1990 - 1994, 1996 - 1998 (Box-folder 001-009)
  - Subseries: - Meeting Minutes
    - Executive Board 1974 - 1979 (Box-folder 002-001)
      Re: Minutes and related documents
    - Executive Board February - October 1980 (Box-folder 002-002)
      Re: Minutes
    - Executive Board February - November 1981 (Box-folder 002-003)
      Re: Minutes, Executive Board and executive sessions
    - Review of Board Minutes September 1981 (Box-folder 002-004)
      Re: Review of board minutes, highlights actions taken 1975 - 1981
    - Executive Board March - December 1983 (Box-folder 002-005)
    - Executive Board February - April 1984 (Box-folder 002-006)
      Re: Minutes, Executive Board
    - Executive Board June 2, 1985 (Box-folder 002-007)
    - Executive Board Motions Manual June 1989 (Box-folder 002-008)
      Re: Motions passed by NAPNAP Executive Board from 1986 to 1989
    - Executive Board April 1991 - October 1992 (Box-folder 002-009)
      Re: Minutes, related documents, board meetings and dates list-1988 - 1992
    - Executive Board March 1995 - October 1996 (Box-folder 002-010)
    - General Business Meetings October 1974, February 1980 - October 1983 (Box-folder 002-011)
      Re: Annual meeting address list 1974 and general business meeting minutes
    - NAPNAP Motions Forms 1989 - 1992 (Box-folder 002-012)
      Re: Motions made by NAPNAP members
  - Subseries: - Correspondence and Related Documents
    - American Academy of Pediatrics/ANA June 1971 (Box-folder 003-001)
      Re: Education for pediatric nurse associates
    - McCleery, Janet: Correspondence July-December 1972 (Box-folder 003-002)
      Re: Plans for formation of NAPNAP
    - McCleery, Janet: Correspondence January-June 1973 (Box-folder 003-003)
      Re: Formation of NAPNAP, membership drive, organizational goals, relations with AAP and ANA, funding
    - McCleery, Janet and Cunningham, Phillis: Correspondence July-December 1973 (Box-folder 003-004)
      Re: Affiliation issues involving ANA and AAP, funding of newsletter by Johnson 7 Johnson, ANA-AAP Liaison Committee, NAPNAP guidelines, ANA PNP Council
    - ANA Reports July - November 1973 (Box-folder 003-005)
      Re: Definition of NP, PNP programs, certification
    - McCleery, Janet & Cunningham, Phillis: Correspondence and Related Documents January 2 - 29, 1974 (Box-folder 003-006)
      Re: NAPNAP conference planning and corporate support, breakdown in communications between AAP & ANA over PNP certification, and responses by PNPs, NAPNAP membership drive
    - McCleery, Janet & Cunningham, Phillis: Correspondence and Related Documents February 1 - March 12, 1974 (Box-folder 003-007)
      Re: Meeting plans, corporate funding/ involvement, certification issues involving NAPNAP, ANA, AAP, including opinions of PNPs
    - McCleery, Janet & Cunningham, Phillis: Correspondence and Related Documents April - June, 1974 (Box-folder 003-008)
      Re: Conference planning, NAPNAP CE seminars, corporate funding of NAPNAP newsletter, continuing education program
    - McCleery, Janet & Cunningham, Phillis: Correspondence and Related Documents July - December, 1974 (Box-folder 003-009)
      Re: Conferences, educational seminars, Silver's efforts to have government support for a NP program, corporate support
    - PNA Certification Committee April 1974 - January 1975 (Box-folder 003-010)
      Re: Documents and correspondence about November 1974 meeting, NAPNAP/ AAP col-aboration to define PNP scope of practice, certification, includes consideration of NLN collaboration in the future.
    - Original Membership 1973/ 1974 July 1973 - October 1974 (Box-folder 003-011)
      Re: Charter members and 1974 members
    - Cunningham, Phillis & McCleery, Janet January 1975 - February 1975 (Box-folder 003-012)
      Re: Newsletter first issue, member endorsement of ANA/ AAP PNP guidelines
    - Cunningham, Phillis & McCleery, Janet March 1975 (Box-folder 003-013)
      Re: Meeting plans, Federation of Specialty Nursing Organizations, continuing education programs, membership
    - Cunningham, Phillis & McCleery, Janet April 1975 (Box-folder 003-014)
      Re: Miscellaneous business including: Federation of Specialty Nursing organizations (Lysaught), certification/ scope of practice, ANA/ NAPNAP relations, continuing educa-tion programs
    - Cunningham, Phillis & McCleery, Janet May 1975 (Box-folder 003-015)
      Re: Miscellaneous business, including: Federation of Nursing Specialty organizations, AAP Affiliation, continuing education programs, membership, PNP programs
    - Cunningham, Phillis & McCleery, Janet June 1975 (Box-folder 003-016)
      Re: Miscellaneous business, including: meeting, continuing education program planning, definition of PNP, physician's assistants
    - Cunningham, Phillis & McCleery, Janet July 1 - 15, 1975 (Box-folder 003-017)
      Re: PNP accreditation, Federation of Specialty Nursing Organizations, NAPNAP newsletter, support from Johnson and Johnson
    - Cunningham, Phillis & McCleery, Janet July 16 - 31, 1975 (Box-folder 003-018)
      Re: Accreditation, affiliation with AAP, miscellaneous
    - Cunningham, Phillis & McCleery, Janet August, 1975 (Box-folder 004-001)
      Re: Miscellaneous business, including AAP affiliation, scope of practice, educational guidelines
    - Cunningham, Phillis & McCleery, Janet September 1975 (Box-folder 004-002)
      Re: Miscellaneous business, including meeting plans, NAPNAP newsletter, physicians assistants, NAPNAP/ AAP/ ANA relations
    - Cunningham, Phillis & McCleery, Janet October 1975 (Box-folder 004-003)
      Re: Miscellaneous business, including annual meeting, NAPNAP newsletter
    - Cunningham, Phillis & McCleery, Janet November 1975 (Box-folder 004-004)
      Re: Certification and accreditation, NAPNAP/ AAP, ANA, NAPNAP logo, NAPNAP national office
    - AAP/ Committee on Pediatric Manpower January 1975 - February 1975 (Box-folder 004-005)
      Re: Accreditation, role of PNP
    - AAP/ Committee on Pediatric Manpower November 1974 - March 1975 (Box-folder 004-006)
      Re: Committee on Pediatric Manpower, documents compiled for March 1975 meeting
    - AAP/ Committee on Pediatric Manpower March 1975 (Box-folder 004-007)
      Re: Certification, role of PNP, qualifying examination
    - AAP/ Committee on Pediatric Manpower April 1975 - July 1975 (Box-folder 004-008)
      Re: PNP scope of practice, practice patterns, school nurse practitioners, accreditation of PNP programs report, PNP/ A's seeking placement
    - Cunningham, Phillis, Committee on Pediatric Manpower September 9 - 10, 1975 (Box-folder 004-009)
      Re: Meeting documents (part 1)
    - Cunningham, Phillis, Committee on Pediatric Manpower September 9 -10, 1975 (Box-folder 004-010)
      Re: Meeting documents (part 2)
    - Cunningham, Phillis, Committee on Pediatric Manpower September 9 - 10, 1975 (Box-folder 004-011)
      Re: Meeting documents (part 3)
    - Committee on Pediatric Manpower September 9 - 10, 1975 (Box-folder 005-001)
      Re: Committee minutes
    - AAP/ Committee on Pediatric Manpower September 1975 (Box-folder 005-002)
      Re: Miscellaneous correspondence about certification and accreditation, Cunningham assessment of the September meeting
    - AAP/ NAPNAP Committee on Accreditation May - October 1975 (Box-folder 005-003)
      Re: Accreditation
    - American Academy of Pediatrics/ NAPNAP January/ March 1975, n.d. (Box-folder 005-004)
      Re: Scope of practice statement NAPNAP/ AAP
    - American Academy of Pediatrics/ NAPNAP April - May 1975 (Box-folder 005-005)
      Re: Responses to PNP Scope of Practice/AAP
    - AAP to Pediatric Nurse Practitioners July 1975 (Box-folder 005-006)
      Re: October 1975 meeting program, immunization
    - NAPNAP, AAP, AFNP, Consortium to Develop PNP Qualifying Exam August 1975 (Box-folder 005-007)
      Re: National qualifying examination
    - ANA/ NAPNAP/ AAP February - June, n.d. 1975 (Box-folder 005-008)
      Re: PNP accreditation
    - AAP/ ANA/ NAPNAP October - November 1975 (Box-folder 005-009)
      Re: NAPNAP/ AAP collaboration on scope of practice, certification, ANA participation
    - ANA/ AAP/ NAPNAP November - December 1975 (Box-folder 005-010)
      Re: Dialogue on certification, accreditation
    - ANA September - October 1975 (Box-folder 005-011)
      Re: ANA testimony to Congress about PRSO, news release about accreditation for continuing education
    - Federation of Specialty Organizations/ ANA January 1975 - February 1976 (Box-folder 005-012)
      Re: 1975 meetings ANA and FSO, Lysaught survey, ANA response
    - Association of Faculties of NA/ P Programs October 1975 (Box-folder 005-013)
      Re: Organization of nurse practitioner faculty
    - Fond, Karen Correspondence (secretary) March 1975 - November 1975 (Box-folder 005-014)
      Re: NAPNAP/ AAP affiliation, scope of practice, differences with ANA over PNP role
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence January - December 1975 (Box-folder 005-015)
      Re: Miscellaneous NAPNAP incorporation, PNP graduates and programs, Wyeth Company relations, 1976 officers election, Johnson and Johnson support of NAPNAP newsletter, membership - PNP grads by state
    - NAPNAP Continuing Education Committee and Other Committees 1975 (Box-folder 005-016)
      Re: Seminars, local arrangements and committees, membership committee, committee chairs guidelines
    - Cunningham, Phillis: Correspondence January - April 1976 (Box-folder 005-017)
      Re: Conferences and meetings: Johnson and Johnson support, AAP input on nurse prac-tioners concerning Bureau of Health Manpower programs (Silver, Frazier), establishment of central office and trademarks, NAPNAP/ AAP collaboration, ANA resolution for certification, preparation of membership brochure
    - Dunn, Barbara: Correspondence February 20, 1976 (Box-folder 005-018)
      Re: Standards of practice, certification examination
    - Cunningham, Phillis and Dunn, Barbara: Correspondence May - July 1976 (Box-folder 005-019)
      Re: NAPNAP/ ANA disagreements over PNP definition, internal business, Henry Silver plaque
    - National Board of PNP/ A & AAP Correspondence March - May, 1976 (Box-folder 005-020)
      Re: ANA participation in certification, PNP certifying examination for 1977
    - Cunningham, Phillis: Correspondence August - September 1976 (Box-folder 005-021)
      Re: Presentation of first Silver Award, internal business
    - AAP/ ANA September 1976 (Box-folder 005-022)
      Re: AAP - ANA participation in accreditation
    - Cunningham, Phillis, McCleery, Janet & Dunn, Barbara October - November 1976 (Box-folder 005-023)
      Re: Conferences, membership, corporate relations, national office, certification examination
    - Cunningham, Phillis, Correspondence December 1976 (Box-folder 005-024)
      Re: Conferences, internal business
    - McCleery, Janet & Cunningham, Phillis: Correspondence January 1977 (Box-folder 006-001)
      Re: Continuing education committee and conferences, internal business
    - Cunningham, Phillis & Dunn, Barbara, Correspondence February 1977 (Box-folder 006-002)
      Re: PNA brochure for Layman, PNA hospital privileges statement, miscellaneous business
    - Cunningham, Phillis: Correspondence March 1977 (Box-folder 006-003)
      Re: Conferences, finances, corporate relations
    - Cunningham, Phillis: Correspondence April 1977 (Box-folder 006-004)
      Re: April 24 1977 Henry Silver Award, miscellaneous business, AAP/ NAPNAP meeting
    - Cunningham, Phillis & Wiswall, Judith: Correspondence May 1977 (Box-folder 006-005)
      Re: Henry Silver Award (McAtee) and miscellaneous business
    - Cunningham, Phillis & Dunn, Barbara: Correspondence June, 1977 (Box-folder 006-006)
      Re: Miscellaneous business, legal advise on state chapters formation
    - Progress Report on Certification June 1977 (Box-folder 006-007)
      Re: Paper presented at Regional Conference in Los Angeles by Patricia McAtee and Peggy Zurflug and commentary paper
    - Cunningham, Phillis & Dunn, Barbara: Correspondence July - September 1977 (Box-folder 006-008)
      Re: Incorporation, conferences, AAP-NAPNAP collaboration
    - Dunn, Barbara & Cunningham, Phillis: Correspondence October - November 1977 (Box-folder 006-009)
      Re: Continuing education programs, conferences, chapters, legal issues about incorporation
    - Cunningham, Phillis: Correspondence December 1977 (Box-folder 006-010)
      Re: Conferences and seminars
    - Conferences August - November 1977 (Box-folder 006-011)
      Re: Attendance, expenses, income for conferences 1974 - 1977, programs and evaluations
    - NAPNAP Committee Listings 1976 - 1977 (Box-folder 006-012)
      Re: Committee members
    - Cunningham, Phillis & Dunn, Barbara: Correspondence January - April 1978 (Box-folder 006-013)
      Re: Conference and meeting plans, support for Janetti, Inc as NAPNAP management firm by Jean Splann, Dunn's comments on regulations for rural health clinics
    - Financial report and 1977 member survey February 1978 (Box-folder 006-014)
      Re: Finances and budget, results of membership survey
    - NAPNAP/ ANA April 5, 1978 (Box-folder 006-015)
      Re: Joint planning committee on preparation of NP literature compilation
    - NBPNPA/ NAPNAP/ AAP (Box-folder 006-016)
      Re: Joint recertification committee minutes
    - Cunningham, Phillis & Dunn, Barbara: Correspondence May - August 1978 (Box-folder 006-017)
      Re: Meetings, malpractice coverage, CEUs
    - Cunningham, Phillis: Correspondence August - October 1978 (Box-folder 006-018)
      Re: Meetings, programs, honorary members, awards, CEUs, SC chapter
    - Education Committee [November?] 1978 (Box-folder 006-019)
      Re: Annual report of committee
    - NAPNAP Long-range Plans April - October 1978 (Box-folder 006-020)
      Re: Long range plans about programs, finances, membership, include input from Johnson and Johnson
    - Conference Proceedings May 11-12, 1978 (Box-folder 006-021)
      Re: Proceedings of first national conference of PNP and association program directors
    - Misc. Officers' Correspondence & 1978 Membership Survey January - December 1979 (Box-folder 006-022)
      Re: Virginia regulation of NP's, NACOG meeting, Nurse Training Act, conference and 1978 membership survey results
    - Dunn, Barbara: Correspondence May 1979 (Box-folder 006-023)
      Re: Appointment of Barbara Dunn as NAPNAP executive director
    - NAPNAP Long-Range Plan October 1979 (Box-folder 006-024)
      Re: Long range plan and mission statement
    - Executive Director and President, Dunn, Barbara & Hicks, M: Correspondence January - May 1980 (Box-folder 007-001)
      Re: ANA/ NAPNAP publication, support of congressional bill, children's programming, recertification process
    - Executive Director and President, Dunn, Barbara & Hicks, M: Correspondence June - August 1980 (Box-folder 007-002)
      Re: Supervision of physicians, NAPNAP/ANA relations, accreditation, recertification
    - Executive Director and President, Dunn, Barbara & Fond, K.: Correspondence September - December 1980 (Box-folder 007-003)
      Re: Certification, legislation, financial
    - Sustaining Member File, 1979 member survey January - June 1980 (Box-folder 007-004)
      Re: Sustaining members, 1979 membership survey results
    - Legislative Committee July - December 1980 (Box-folder 007-005)
      Re: Members, 1981 NAPNAP legislative platform, and legislative manual
    - Executive Director and President, Dunn, B, Fond, K. & McCleery, J.: Correspondence January - May 1981 (Box-folder 007-006)
      Re: Children's television advertising, state certification, executive director position, NAPNAP office management, support for legislation
    - Executive Director and President, McGuire, M & Fond, K.: Correspondence July - December 1981 (Box-folder 007-007)
      Re: Personnel/Executive Director, nurse midwives certification, long range plan, legislative platform
    - Executive Director and President, McGuire, M & Nystrom, J.: Correspondence January - December 1982 (Box-folder 007-008)
      Re: ACNM Board, Johnson and Johnson travel fellowships, NAPNAP executive director, NAPNAP office management by Janetti, NAPNAP trademark
    - President Elect, Rudy, C.: Correspondence January - August 1982 (Box-folder 007-009)
      Re: Model nurse practice act
    - Long Range Plan October 1982 (Box-folder 007-010)
      Re: Long Range Plan 1983 - 1988
    - Legislative Committee July 1982 (Box-folder 007-011)
      Re: Revised legislative manual, influencing your legislator, 1983 NAPNAP legislative platform
    - Executive Director, McGuire, M.: Correspondence January - December 1983 (Box-folder 007-012)
      Re: South Carolina nursing legislation, Janetti Inc services to NAPNAP, task force on nurse practice act
    - President Rudy, C. & Jonides, L., Chapter coordinator: Correspondence April - December 1983 (Box-folder 007-013)
      Re: Janetti contract renewal, Janetti services in publishing Pediatric Nursing journal, model nurse practice act, Johnson and Johnson travel fellowships
    - President, Walsh, S.: Correspondence May - November 1983 (Box-folder 007-014)
      Re: Nurse practice acts, Brazilian nurses, B. Bullough on nurse practice acts and prescription authority, contract with Janetti Inc to manage NAPNAP central office
    - Miscellaneous Officers Information October - November 1983 (Box-folder 007-015)
      Re: Executive board and staff, President's schedule, membership list availability policy
    - Annual Membership Survey and Totals May 1983 (Box-folder 007-016)
      Re: Annual membership survey and totals
    - NAPNAP Scope of Practice Questionnaire (Box-folder 007-017)
      Re: Questionnaire results
    - Executive Director and President, McGuire, M. & Rudy, C.: Correspondence January - November 1984 (Box-folder 007-018)
      Re: Slack Inc office services, Janetti services, accounting
    - Executive Director and President, McGuire, M. & Rudy, C.: Correspondence May - October 1984 (Box-folder 007-019)
      Re: ANA statement on NP scope of practice, responsibilities of NAPNAP executive director, nurse practice acts, report to members, NAPNAP Foundation, Johnson and Johnson sponsorship, copyright
    - Walsh, S to Rudy, C. and Executive Board May 24, 1984 (Box-folder 007-020)
      Re: Long range plan and conference planning
    - Statement of Goals, Scholarships and Grants March - April 1984 (Box-folder 007-021)
      Re: Statement of Goals for NAPNAP, NAPNAP McNeil Scholarships and Grants
    - NAPNAP Committees April - June 1984 (Box-folder 007-022)
      Re: Legislative platform, procedures for 1984, report of Ad Hoc committee on National NP organization, chapter committee to chapter residents concerning continuing education process
    - NAPNAP Membership Report 1976 - 1984 (Box-folder 007-023)
      Re: NAPNAP membership totals report
    - Executive Director, McGuire, M.: Correspondence January - September 1985 (Box-folder 008-001)
      Re: Tax exempt status, lobbying services for NAPNAP
    - McNeil Scholarship and Travel Grant January - December 1985 (Box-folder 008-002)